<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="cll-ja_20.xsl" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
	<!ENTITY quantifier "数量詞">
	<!ENTITY free_modifier "自由修飾句">
]>

<chapter number="20">

<meta>
<title>CLL 第20章 セルマホ目録</title>
<author>iocikun.juj</author>
</meta>

<body>
<link>
<prev><name>第19章</name><address>./chapter19.html</address></prev>
<next><name>第21章</name><address>./chapter21.html</address></next>
</link>
<image>./images/chapter20.gif</image>

<body_>
<before>
<chu># 下書き</chu>
<chu># 訳の清書中</chu>
<chu># 予定: xml の構造をきれいにする</chu>
<chu># 予定: xslt によって作られる xhtml を validation に通るものにする</chu>
<chu># 予定: 41 の note を check し、それらを削除する (28/41)</chu><br />
<chu># 予定: 121 のセルマホの訳を見直す</chu><br/>
<chu># 予定: 訳語の統一(この章のなかで統一したうえで vlaste に追加する)</chu><br/>
<chu># 予定: 疑問点、訳の代換案、学ぶべきところを comment としてまとめる</chu><br/>
<chu># 予定: IE での表示をチェックする(今のところ firefox での動作確認)</chu><br/>
<chu># 予定: つっこみ待ち、かつ時々チェックして修正していく</chu><br/>
<ppp>まずは note 部分の見直し。それぞれに番号をふろう</ppp>
<ppp>41個の note がある</ppp>
</before>

<h2>CLL 第20章 セルマホ目録</h2>
<ppp>Chapter 20 A Catalogue of selma'o</ppp>

<p>
以下の段落では、ロジバンのセルマホ全てを列挙し簡単な説明を加えた。
詳細はそれぞれの章を参照すること。
セルマホの名前は代表的なシマヴォの
大文字表記(「h」は「'」の大文字とする)で表す。
代表的なシマヴォには最も重要なものか、
またはアルファベット順で一番目にくるものが選ばれる。
それぞれについて、ひとつずつ例文を挙げる。
セルマホの使いかたは複数あるが、そのなかで最も一般的な用法を示す。
</p>

<ppp>The following paragraphs list all the selma'o of Lojban, with a brief
explanation of what each one is about, and reference to the chapter number where
each is explained more fully.</ppp>
<ppp>As usual, all selma'o names are given in capital letters
(with "h" serving as the capital of "'") and
are the names of a representative cmavo, often the most important or the first
in alphabetical order.</ppp>
<ppp>One example is given of each selma'o: for selma'o which have several uses,
the most common use is shown.</ppp>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ A (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<ppp>selma'o A (Chapter 14)</ppp>
<p>論理的なつながり(例: かつ、または、もし)を示す。主にスムティ同士の接続に使う。
<ppp>Specifies a logical connection (e.g. "and", "or", "if"), usually
between sumti.</ppp>
<ppp>John and/or Jane goes to the store</ppp></p>
<pre>la djan. .ala djein. klama le zarci
(ジャンとジェーンのどちらかまたは両方が店に行く。)</pre>
<p>bu を後置して、母音のレルフ(文字)そのものを表す語を作る。<br/>
<chu># 訳注: abu, ebu, ibu, obu, ubu, ybu がそれぞれ文字
a, e, i, o, u, y を表すということ</chu>
<ppp>Also used to create vowel lerfu words when followed with "bu".</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ BAI (<a href="./chapter9.html">第9章</a>)
<ppp>selma'o BAI (Chapter 9)</ppp></h3>
<p>
セルブリの構造に表現したい関係を表す場所がなかった場合に、
スムティに前置することでその場所を追加することができる。
セルブリから派生し、それの持つ場所のひとつからその意味が決まる。
<ppp>May be prefixed to a sumti to specify an additional place, not otherwise
present in the place structure of the selbri, and derived from a single place
of some other selbri.</ppp>
<pre>mi tavla bau la lojban.
(私はロジバン語で話す。)</pre>
<ppp>I speak in-language Lojban.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ BAhE (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>
後に続く一語を強調する。
またはそれが臨時語(その場で作った単語)であることを示す。
<ppp>Emphsizes the next single word, or marks it as a nonce word
(one invented for the occasion).</ppp>
<pre>la ba'e .djordj. klama le zarci
(店に来たのはジョージだ。)</pre>
<ppp>George goes to the store.</ppp>
<ppp>It is George who goes to the store.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ BE (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>)</h3>
<p>タンルを形成するひとつの要素の持つ場所にスムティをいれる。
指定がなければそのスムティは x2, x3 ... と次に来る場所にはいる。
BE は LE による描写のなかで最も有用だ。
BEI や BEhO も見よ。
<ppp>Attaches sumti which fill the place structure of a single unit making
up a tanru.</ppp>
<ppp>Unless otherwise indicated, the sumti fill the x2, x3, and successive places
in  that order. BE is most useful in descriptions formed with LE. See BEI, BEhO.
</ppp>
<pre>mi klama be ta troci
(私はあそこに行こうとする。)</pre>
<ppp>I am-a-(goer to-that) type-of trier. I try to go to that place.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: klama の x1 が troci を修飾し、その次の場所である x2 に ta
がはいる</chu></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ BEI (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>)</h3>
<p>BE によってタンルの構成単位に付加された複数のスムティ同士を分ける。
<ppp>Separates multiple sumti attached by BE to a tanru unit.</ppp>
<pre>mi klama be le zarci bei le zdani be'o troci
(私は家から店に行こうとする。)</pre>
<ppp>I am-a-(goer to-the store from-the home) type-of-trier.
I try to go from the home to the market</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: klama の x1 が troci を修飾し、その次の場所である x2 に le zarci が
さらにその次の場所である x3 に bei で分けられた le zdani がはいる</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ BEhO (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>)</h3>
<p>
BE に対する省略可能な終端詞。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for BE. </ppp>
タンルの構成単位に付加されたスムティを終わらせる。
<ppp>Terminates sumti that are attached to a tanru unit.</ppp>
<pre>mi klama be le zarci be'o troci
(私は店に行こうとする。)</pre>
<ppp>I am-a-(goer to-the market) type-of-trier. I try to go to the market.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ BIhE (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>
数学演算子の前につけて、他の数学演算子よりも優先度が高いことを示す。
この演算子の前後の被演算子はより強く結びつく。
<ppp>Prefix attached to a mathematical operator to mark it as higher priority
than other mathematical operators, binding its operands more closely.</ppp>
<pre>li ci bi'e pi'i vo su'i mu du li paze
(3 * 4 + 5 = 17)</pre>
<ppp>The-number 3 [priority] times 4 plus 5 equals the-number 17.</ppp>
<ppp>3 * 4 + 5 = 17</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: 原著では pi'i ではなく pi'u となっていたが pi'i
が正しいと思われる</chu><br/>
<chu># 訳注: bi'e によって pi'i(かけ算) のほうが先に計算されることが明示されている
</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ BIhI (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<p>
スムティまたはタンルの構成単位(あるいはそれ以外の何か)を結びつけることで、
範囲を表す。
GAhO も見よ。
<ppp>Joins sumti or tanru units (as well as some other things) to form
intervals. See GAhO.</ppp>
<pre>mi ca sanli la drezdn. bi'i la frankfurt.
(私はドレスデンとフランクフルトの間に立つ。)
</pre>
<ppp>I am standing between Dresden and Frankfurt.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ BO (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>, <a href="./chapter15.html">第15章</a>, <a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>タンルの構成単位を強く結合する。
<ppp>Joins tanru units, binding them together closely.</ppp>
論理的にまたは非論理的に、節や文などを結合するのに使える。
<ppp>Also used to bind logically or non-logically connected phrases, sentences,
etc.</ppp>
結合において BO は常に優先され、また右結合である。
<ppp>BO is always high precedence and right-grouping.</ppp>
<pre>ta cmalu nixli bo ckule
(あれは女の子のための小さな学校だ。)
</pre>
<ppp>That is-a-small type-of (girl type-of school).</ppp>
<ppp>That is small school for girls.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: ta cmalu (nixli bo ckule) のように結合する。
bo がなければ、ta (cmalu nixli) ckule のように左から結合し、
「(小さな女の子)のための学校」となる。
</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ BOI (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>
PA や BY のための省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for PA or BY.</ppp>
数(数を表すシマヴォの列)やレルフ列(文字の列)に別の列がすぐに続くときに、
それらを終わらせるために使われる。
<ppp>Used to terminate a number (string of numeric cmavo) or lerfu string
(string of letter words) when another string immediately follows.</ppp>
<pre>li re du li vu'u voboi re
(数 2 は数 4 と 2 の差と等しい。)</pre>
<ppp>The-number two equals the-number the-difference-of four-and two.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: voboi re でなく vore とすると 42 になってしまう</chu>
</p>
<!-- 10/121 -->
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ BU (<a href="./chapter17.html">第17章</a>)</h3>
<p>
全ての語の後置することができる。
主にアルファベットの文字またはその名前に後置し、
記号やその他のアルファベットの文字を表す語を作る。
<ppp>A suffix which can be attached to any word, typically a word representing
a letter of the alphabet or else a name, to make a word for a symbol or
a different letter of the alphabet.</ppp>
特にひとつの母音だけから成るシマヴォにつけることで、それを表す語として使われる。
<ppp>In paticular, attached to single-vowel cmavo to make words for vowel
letters.</ppp>
<pre>.abu .ebu .ibu .obu .ubu .ybu
("a", "e", "i", "o", "u", "y")</pre></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ BY (<a href="./chapter17.html">第17章</a>)</h3>
<p>
ロジバンにおける文字を表す語と文字を表す語の解釈を変えるためのシフト記号の役割を果たす語。
<ppp>Words representing the letters of the Lojban alphabet, plus various
shift words which alter the interpretation of other letter words.</ppp>
<pre>.abu tavla .by le la .ibymym. skami
(A は B に IBM のコンピュータについて話す。)</pre>
<ppp>A talks-to B about-the of-IBM computers.</ppp>
<ppp>A talks to B about IBM computers.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: IBM をロジバンの名前にするためにはそれぞれの文字 ibu by my をつなげて、
最後に子音をつけて、.ibubymym.
とする。母音の後の bu を省略して .ibymym. とできる。</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ CAI (<a href="./chapter13.html">第13章</a>)</h3>
<p>感情の程度(最高に、強く、弱く、全くない)を表す品詞。
<ppp>A particle which indicates the intensity of an emotion: maximum,
strong, weak, or not at all.</ppp>
たいていは感情を表す他の品詞の後に続ける。
<ppp>Typically follows another particle which specifies the emotion.</ppp>
<pre>.ei cai mi klama le zarci
(店に行かなければならない。)</pre>
<ppp>[Oblication!][Intense!]I go-to the market.</ppp>
<ppp>I must go to the market.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: .ei は義務を表す心態詞。eicai は強い義務を表現する。</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ CAhA (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>ブリディが事実、可能性、能力のいずれを表しているのかを決める。
<ppp>Specifies whether a bridi refers to an actual fact,
a potential (achieved or not), or merely an innate capability.</ppp>
<pre>ro datka ka'e flulimna
(全てのアヒルは浮かんで泳ぐことができる。)</pre>
<ppp>all ducks [capability] are-float-swimmers</ppp>
<ppp>All ducks have the capability of swimming by floating.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ CEI (<a href="./chapter7.html">第7章</a>)</h3>
<p>セルブリによる記述を5個の代ブリディ(broda, brode, brodi, brodo, brodu)
のうちのひとつに代入する。
<ppp>Assigns a selbri definition to one of the five pro-bridi gismu:
"broda", "brode", "brodi", "brodo", or "brodu", for later use.</ppp>
<pre>ti slasi je mlatu bo cidja lante gacri cei broda
.i le crino broda cu barda .i le xunre broda cu cmalu
(これはプラスティックのキャットフード缶の蓋だ。
緑のは大きい。赤いのは小さい。)</pre>
<ppp>This is a plastic cat-food can cover, or thingy.
The green thingy is large. The red thingy is small.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ CEhE (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>, <a href="./chapter16.html">第16章</a>)</h3>
<p>複数の名辞を名辞組にまとめる。
<ppp>Joins multiple terms into a termset.</ppp>
名辞組はそれぞれの名辞を関係づけ、論理的に接続し、&quantifier;の掛かる範囲をまとめ、
または特別な間制の構造を作るために使われる。
<ppp>Termsets are used to associate several terms for logical connectives,
for equal quantifier scope, or for special constructs in tenses.</ppp><br/>
<chu># 訳注: 「量を示す詞のかかる範囲をまとめ」るとは
「3匹の犬が2人の人にかみついた」という文章において
3匹の犬が「同じ」2人の人にという意味を示すということ</chu><br/>
<chu># 訳注: 「特別な間制の構造」については訳者の理解が足りない。例文が必要</chu><br/>
<pre>mi ce'e do pe'e je la djan. ce'e la djeimyz. cu pendo
(私は君の友達で、ジョーンはジェームズの友達だ。)</pre>
<ppp>I [,] you [joint] and John [,] James are-friends-of.</ppp>
<ppp>I am a friend of you, and John is a friend of James.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ CO (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>)</h3>
<p>
タンルの構成要素の間に置かれ、それをひっくりかえす。
つまり、後続するタンルの構成単位が先行するタンルの構成単位を修飾するようにする。
<ppp>When inserted between the components of a tanru, inverts it, so
that the following tanru unit modifies the previous one.</ppp>
<pre>mi troci co klama zarci le zdani
(私は家から店に行ってみる。)</pre>
<ppp>I am-a-trier of-type (goer to-the market from-the house).</ppp>
<ppp>I try to go to the market from the house.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: CO は修飾のしかたはひっくり返すが場所は後のセルブリのものを取る。</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ COI (<a href="./chapter6.html">第6章</a>, <a href="./chapter13.html">第13章</a>)</h3>
<p>名前や描写、スムティに前置し呼格を形成する。
呼格は誰に(または誰が)話しているのかを示す。
<ppp>When prefixed to a name, description, or sumti, produces a vocative:
a phrase which indicates who is being spoken to (or who is speaking).</ppp>
呼格は挨拶や別れ、無線通信等、会話の場面において使われる。
DOI, DOhU も見よ。
<ppp>Vocatives are used in conversational protocols, includeing greeting,
farewell, and radio communication. </ppp><ppp>See DOI, DOhU.</ppp>
<pre>coi .djan.
(今日は、ジョン。)</pre>
<ppp>Greetings, John.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ CU (<a href="./chapter9.html">第9章</a>)</h3>
<p>ブリディ内で、前にあるスムティからセルブリを分ける。
<ppp>Separates the selbri of a bridi from any sumti which precede it.</ppp>
厳密に言うと必要ないのだが、いろいろな終端子を省略するのに役立つ。
<ppp>Never strictly necessary, but often useful to eliminate various elidable
terminators.</ppp>
<pre>le gerku cu klama le zarci
(犬が店に行く。)</pre>
<ppp>The dog goes to-the store.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ CUhE (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>「いつ」、「どこで」、または、「どんな状況であればそのブリディが成り立つか」、
を尋ねる疑問文を作る。PU、CAHA、TAhE、BAI も見よ。
<ppp>Forms a question which asks when, where, or in what mode the rest of the
bridi is true.</ppp><ppp>See PU, CAhA, TAhE, and BAI.</ppp>
<pre>do cu'e klama le zarci
(いつ店に行くのですか。)</pre>
<ppp>You [When/Where?] go to-the store?</ppp>
<ppp>When are you going to the store?</ppp></p>
<!-- 20/121 -->
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ DAhO (<a href="./chapter7.html">第7章</a>)</h3>
<p>代スムティ(KOhA)や代ブリディ(GOhA)への代入を取り消す。
<ppp>Cancels the assigned significance of all sumti cmavo (of selma'o KOhA)
and bridi cmavo (of selma'o GOhA).</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ DOI (<a href="./chapter13.html">第13章</a>)</h3>
<p>汎用的な呼格。
<ppp>The non-specific vocative indicator.</ppp>
COI とともに、または単独で用いられる。
<ppp>May be used with or without COI.</ppp>
doi と後続する名前のあいだに停止は必用ない。
<ppp>No pause is required between "doi" and a following name.</ppp>
DOhU も見よ。
<ppp>See DOhU.</ppp>
<pre>doi frank. mi tavla do
(フランク。私は君に話している。)</pre>
<ppp>O Frank, I speak-to you.</ppp>
<ppp>Frank, I'm talking to you.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ DOhU (<a href="./chapter13.html">第13章</a>)</h3>
<p>
COI や DOI の省略可能な終端子。呼びかけの終わりを示す。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for COI or DOI. Signals the end of a vocative.</ppp>
<pre>coi do'u
(やあ、誰か。)</pre>
<ppp>Greetings [terminator]</ppp><ppp>Greetings, O unspecified one!</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ FA (<a href="./chapter9.html">第9章</a>)</h3>
<p>スミティの前につけて、セルマホの何番目の場所に入るのかを示す。
語順よりも優先される。
<ppp>Prefix for a sumti, indicating which numbered place in the place
structure the sumti belongs in; overrides word order.</ppp>
<pre>fa mi cu klama fi la .atlantas. fe la bastn.
fo le dargu fu le karce
(私はアトランタからボストンへその道を通って車で行く。)</pre>
<ppp>x1 = I go x3 = Atlanta x2 = Boston x4 = the road x5 = the car</ppp>
<ppp>I go from Atlanta to Boston via the road using the car.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ FAhA (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>
どこでそのブリディの示す事がらが起きたかの方向を示す。
MOhI をつけるとその方向への動きという意味になり、
VEhA や VIhA を前置してその方向に沿ってという意味となる。
<ppp>Specifies the direction in which, or toward which (when marked with
MOhI) or along which (when prefixed by VEhA or VIhA) the action of the bridi
takes place</ppp>
<pre>le nanmu zu'a batci le gerku
(私の左で男が犬をかむ。)</pre>
<ppp>The man [left] bites the dog.</ppp>
<ppp>To my left, the man bites the dog.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ FAhO (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>文法的な要素ではない機械的なしるし。文章の終わりを示す。
コンピュータへの入力の際に有用。
<ppp>A mechanical signal, outside the grammar, indicating that there is no
more text. Useful in talking to computers.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ FEhE (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>
期間を表す(TAhE、ROI、ZAhO によって作られる)限定詞が後続し、
それらが時間ではなく空間的な意味を表すことを示す。
<ppp>Indicates that the following interval modifier (using TAhE, ROI, or
ZAhO) refers to space rather than time.</ppp>
<pre>ko vi'i fe'e di'i sombo le gurni
(穀物を一列に等間隔にまきなさい。)</pre>
<ppp>You-imperative [1-dimensional][space][regularly] sow  the grain.</ppp>
<ppp>Sow the grain in a line and evenly!</ppp></p>
</item>

<!-- 27/121 -->

<item>
<h3>セルマホ FEhU (<a href="./chapter9.html">第9章</a>)</h3>
<p>
FIhO の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for FIhO.</ppp>
その場で作られた法制タグの終わりを示す。
タグ付けられるスミティが後ろに付く。
<ppp>Indicates the end of an ad hoc modal tag: the tagged sumti immediately
follows.</ppp>
<pre>mi viska do fi'o kanla [fe'u] le zunle
(私は左目で君を見る。)</pre>
<ppp>I see you [modal] eye: the left-thing</ppp>
<ppp>I see you with the left eye.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ FIhO (<a href="./chapter9.html">第9章</a>)</h3>
<p>
セルブリの前につけてセルブリを法制タグを作る。
新たに作られた法制タグは文法的にも意味論的にもセルマホ BAI と同等である。
<ppp>When placed before a selbri, transforms the selbri into a modal tag,
grammatically and semantically equivalent to a member of selma'o BAI.</ppp>
<pre>mi viska do fi'o kanla le zunle
(私は左目で君を見る。)</pre>
<ppp>I see you with eye the left-thing</ppp>
<ppp>I see you with my left eye.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ FOI (<a href="./chapter17.html">第17章</a>)</h3>
<p>TEI によって開始された、複合的に構成されたアルファベットの文字名の終わりを示す。
<ppp>Signals the end of a compound alphabet letter word that begins with
TEI.</ppp>
この終端詞は省略できない。
<ppp>Not an elidable terminator.</ppp>
<pre>tei .ebu .akut. bu foi
(アキュートアクセント記号付きの e)</pre>
<ppp>("e" "acute")</ppp>
<ppp>the letter "e" with an acute accent</ppp></p>
<!-- 30/121 -->
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ FUhA (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>
後続する数式を逆ポーランド記法(RP)で解釈させる。
逆ポーランド記法とは、数学演算子を被演算子の後に置く記法である。
<ppp>Indicates that the following mathematical expression is to be
interpreted as reverse Polish (RP), a mode in which mathematical
operators follow their operands.</ppp>
<pre>li fu'a reboi re[boi] su'i du li vo
(2 + 2 = 4)</pre>
<ppp>the-number [RP!] two, two, plus equals the-number four</ppp>
<ppp>2 + 2 = 4</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ FUhE (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>UI に属する心態詞が後続し、
普通そうであるようにその指標が先行する語にかかるのではなく、
後続する語にかかるようにする。その効果は fu'o で終わる。
<ppp>Indicates that the following indicator(s) of selma'o UI affect not the
preceding word, as usual, but rather all following words until a FUhO.</ppp>
<pre>mi viska le fu'e .ia blanu zdani fu'o ponse
(私は、私が青い家だと信じているもの、の所有者を見る。)</pre>
<ppp>I see the [start][belief] blue house [end] prossessor</ppp>
<ppp>I see the  owner of a blue bouse, or what I believe to be one.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ FUhO (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>
UI に属する指標の効果を終わらせる。
<ppp>Cancels all indicators of selma'o UI which are in effect.</ppp>
<pre>mi viska le fu'e .ia blanu zdani fu'o ponse
(私は、私が青い家だと信じているもの、の所有者を見る。)</pre>
<ppp>I see the [start][belief] blue house [end] possessor</ppp>
<ppp>I see the owner of what I believe to be a blue house.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ GA (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<p>
論理的に接続された2つのスミティやブリディ末端などの始まりを示す。
<ppp>Indicates the beginning of two logically connected sumti, bridi-tails,
or various other things.</ppp>
論理的接続とは「以下の両方が成り立つ ... と ...」や
「以下のどちらかまたは両方が成り立つ ... と ...」や
「もし ... ならば ...」等を含む。GI も見よ。
<ppp>Logical connections include "both ... and",
"either ... or", "if ... then", and so on. See GI.</ppp>
<pre>ga la djan. nanmu gi la djeimyz. ninmu
(ジョンが男か、またはジェイムズが女か、またはその両方だ。)</pre>
<ppp>Either John is a man or James is a woman (or both)</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ GAhO (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<p>BIhI によって表される範囲が端点を含むかどうかを示す。
<ppp>Specifies whether an interval specified by BIhI includes or excludes its
endpoints.</ppp>
2つが組で使われて、BIhI シュマボの前後に置かれ、それぞれ左右の端点の性質を決める。
<ppp>Used in pairs before and after the BIhI cmavo, to specify the nature of both
the left- and the right-hand endpoints.</ppp>
<pre>mi ca sanli la drezdn. ga'o bi'i ga'o la frankfurt.
(私はドレスデンとフランクフルトの両方を含む間に立っている。)</pre>
<ppp>I [present] stand Dresden [inclusive][interval][inclusive] Frankfurt.</ppp>
<ppp>I am standing between Dresden and Frankfurt, inclusive of both.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ GEhU (<a href="./chapter8.html">第8章</a>)</h3>
<p>
GOI の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for GOI. </ppp>
関係句の終わりを示す。
<ppp>Marks the end of a relative phrase.</ppp>
KUhO も見よ。
<ppp>See KUhO.</ppp>
<pre>la djan. goi ko'a ge'u blanu
(ジョン(以下 #1 と呼ぶ)は青い。)</pre>
<ppp>John (referred to as #1) is-blue.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ GI (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<p>GA、GUhA、JOI といった前置論理接続詞に後置し、
2つの論理的に、または非論理的に接続されたスムティ、タンルの構成単位、
ブリディ末端等を分ける。
<ppp>Separates two logically or non-logically connected sumti, tanru units,
bridi-tails, or other things, when the prefix is a forethought logical
connective involving GA, GUhA, or JOI.</ppp>
<pre>ge la djan. nanmu gi la dieimyz. ninmu
ジャンは男であり、かつジェームズは女である。</pre>
<ppp>(It is true that) both John is a man and James is a woman.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ GIhA (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<p>
2つのブリディ末端が先行するスムティを持たず、
またいくつかの後続するスムティを持つ場合に、
それらを論理的に(つまり、「かつ」、「または」、「もし」によって)接続する。
<ppp>Specifies a logical connective (e.g. "and", "or", "if") between two
bridi-tails: a bridi-tail is a selbri with any associated following sumti,
but not including an preceding sumti.</ppp>
<pre>mi klama le zarci gi'e nelci la djan.
(私は店に行くし、ジョンが好きだ。)</pre>
<ppp>I  go-to the market and like John</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ GOI (<a href="./chapter8.html">第8章</a>)</h3>
<p>関係句の開始を示す。
従属する(後続する)スムティが別の(先行する)スムティに関係づけられる。
<ppp>Specifies the beginning of a relative phrase, which associates a
subordinate sumti (following) to another sumti (preceding).</ppp>
GEhU や NOI も見よ。
<ppp>See GEhU, NOI.</ppp>
<pre>la djan. goi ko'a cu blanu
(ジョン(以下 #1 と呼ぶ)は青い。)</pre>
<ppp>John (referred to as #1) is blue.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ GOhA (<a href="./chapter7.html">第7章</a>)</h3>
<p>ブリブラの代わりとなる全てのシュマボを含む全般的なセルマホ。
<ppp>A general selma'o for all cmavo which can take the place of brivla.</ppp>
いくつかのグループに分けられる。
<ppp>There are several groups of these.</ppp>
<pre>A: mi klama le zarci B: mi go'i
A: 私は店に行く。B: 私も。</pre>
<ppp>A: I'm going to the market. B: Me, too.</ppp></p>
<!-- 40/121 -->
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ GUhA (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<p>論理的に接続された2つのタンルの構成単位の始まりを示す。
<ppp>Indicates the beginning of two logically connected tanru units.</ppp>
論理的に接続されたタンルを形成するときに GA の代わりに使う。GI も見よ。
<ppp>Takes the place of GA when forming logically-connected tanru. See GI.</ppp>
<pre>la .alis. gu'e ricfu gi blanu
(アリスは裕福で青い。)</pre>
<ppp>Alice is both rich and blue</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ I (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>2つの文を分ける。
<ppp>Separates two sentences from each other.</ppp>
<pre>mi klama le zarci .i mi klama le zdani
(私は店に行く。私は事務所に行く。)</pre>
<ppp>I go-to the market. I go-to the office.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ JA (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<p>2つのタンル、数学被演算子、間制、抽象化の間の論理的接続を示す。
<ppp>Specifies a logical connection (e.g. "and", "or", "if") between two tanru
units, mathematical operands, tenses, or abstractions.</ppp>
<pre>ti blanu je zdani
(これは青い、そして家だ。)</pre>
<ppp>This is-blue and a-house</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ JAI (<a href="./chapter9.html">第9章</a>)</h3>
<p>間制または法制を後置して、セルブリにつけて法制場所でセルブリの x1 を
置き換える演算子を作る。
<ppp>When followed by a tense or modal, creates a conversion operator
attachable to a selbri which exchanges the modal place with the x1 place of the
selbri.</ppp>
単独で使われると、取り除かれたブリディの場所のひとつで、
セルブリの x1 (x1 は抽象スムティでなければならない)を置き換える。
<ppp>When alone, is a conversion operotor exchanging the x1 place of the selbri
(which should be an abstract sumti) with one of the places of the
abstracted-over bridi.</ppp>
<pre>mi jai gau galfi le bitmu skari
(私は壁の色を変える。)</pre>
<ppp>I am-the-actor-in modifying the wall color.</ppp>
<ppp>I act so as to modify the wall color.</ppp>
<ppp>I change the color of the wall.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: 後者の例として、mi jai rinka le nu do morsi がある。</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ JOI (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<p>2つのスムティ、タンルの構成単位等の非論理的接続(例:
集団として、あるいは組として、または並びとして、一緒に)を示す。
<ppp>Specifies a non-logical connection (e.g. together-with-as-mass, -set,
or -sequence) between two sumti, tanru units, or various other things.</ppp>
または、GI を後置して、GA のような前置非論理接続詞を作る。
<ppp>When immediately followed by GI, provides forethought non-logical connection
analogous to GA.</ppp>
<pre>la djan. joi la .alis. cu bevri le pipno
(ジョンはアリスと一緒にピアノを運ぶ。)</pre>
<ppp>John massed-with Alice carry the piano.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ JOhI (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>後続する数学被演算子(TEhU で終わるリスト)が数学のベクトル(一次元配列)で
あることを示す。
<ppp>Indicates that the following mathematical operands (a list terminated by
TEhU) form a mathematical vector (one-dimensional array).</ppp>
<pre>li jo'i paboi reboi te'u su'i jo'i ciboi voboi
du li jo'i voboi xaboi
((1, 2) + (3, 4) = (4, 6))</pre>
<ppp>the-number array(one, two) plus array (three, four) equals the-number
array (four, six)</ppp>
<ppp>(1, 2) + (3, 4) = (4, 6)</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ KE (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>)</h3>
<p>論理的接続やタンル形成等のために KE と後続する KEhE
で囲まれた部分をグループ化する。
<ppp>Groups everything between itself and a following KEhE for purposes of
logical connection, tanru construction, or other purposes.</ppp>
KE と KEhE は数式(VEI、VEhO を見よ)や、談話系(TO、TOI を見よ)には使えない。
<ppp>KE and KEhE are not used for mathematical (see VEI and VEhO) or discursive
(see TO and TOI) purposes.</ppp>
<pre>ta ke melbi cmalu ke'e nixli ckule
(あれは可愛い小ささを持った女の子のための学校だ。)</pre>
<ppp>That is-a-(pretty little) girl school.</ppp>
<ppp>That is a school for girls who are pretty in their littleness.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ KEI (<a href="./chapter11.html">第11章</a>)</h3>
<p>
NU の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for NU.</ppp>
抽象化ブリディの終わりを示す。
<ppp>Marks the end of an abstraction bridi.</ppp>
<pre>la djan. cu nu sonci kei djica
(ジョンは兵士になりたい。)</pre>
<ppp>John is-an-(event-of being-a-soldier) type-of desirer.</ppp>
<ppp>John wants to be a soldier.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ KEhE (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>)</h3>
<p>
KE の省略可能な終端子。グループ化の終わりを示す。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for KE.</ppp><ppp>Marks the end of a grouping.</ppp>
<pre>ta ke melbi cmalu ke'e nixli ckule
(あれは可愛い小ささを持った女の子の学校だ。)</pre>
<ppp>That is-a-(pretty little) girl school.</ppp>
<ppp>That is a school for girls who are pretty in their littleness.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ KI (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>
間制の後につけて、「貼り付き」にする。
つまり、再び KI が現われるまでのすべてのブリディに掛かるようにする。
<ppp>When preceded by a tense, makes it "sticky", so that it applies to all
further bridi until reset by another appearance of KI.</ppp>
単独で使われると、すべての貼り付き間制を引き剥がす。
<ppp>When alone, eliminates all sticky tenses.</ppp></p>
<!-- 50/121 -->
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ KOhA (<a href="./chapter7.html">第7章</a>)</h3>
<p>代スムティとして使われるすべてのシュマボを総称するセルマホ。
<ppp>A general selma'o which contains all cmavo which can substitute for
sumti.</ppp>
これらはいくつかのグループに分けられる。
<ppp>These cmavo are divided into several groups.</ppp>
<pre>le blanu zdani goi ko'a cu barda .i ko'a na cmamau ti
(青い家(以下 #1 と呼ぶ)は大きい。#1 はこれより小さくない。)</pre>
<ppp>The blue house (referred to as #1) is big.
#1 is-not smaller-than this-thing.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ KU (<a href="./chapter6.html">第6章</a>, <a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>LE または、一部の使いかたをした場合の LA の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for LE and some uses of LA.</ppp>
描写スムティの終わりを示す。
<ppp>Indicates the end of a description sumti.</ppp>
また、間制や法制の後に置いて、それらがスムティを取らないことを示す他、
NA+KU の形で自然言語形式の否定を表す。
<ppp>Also used after a tense or modal to indicate that no sumti follows,
and in the compound NA+KU to indicate natural language-style negation.</ppp>
<pre>le prenu ku le zdani ku klama
(その人は家に行く。)</pre>
<ppp>The person, to-the house, goes.</ppp>
<ppp>The person goes to the house.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ KUhE (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>PEhO の省略可能な終端子。数式の前置記法の終わりを示す
(前置記法では演算子が被演算子の前につく)。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for PEhO: indicates the end of a forethought
mathematical expression (one in which the operator precedes the operands).</ppp>
<pre>li pe'o su'i reboi reboi re[boi] ku'e du li xa
(2 2 2 を合計した数は数 6 と等しい。)</pre>
<ppp>The number [forethought] the-sum-of two two two [end] equals the-number
six</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ KUhO (<a href="./chapter8.html">第8章</a>)</h3>
<p>
NOI の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for NOI.</ppp>
関係節の終わりを示す。
<ppp>Indicates the end of a relative clause.</ppp>
<pre>le zdani poi blanu ku'o barda
(その青い家は大きい。)</pre>
<ppp>The house which is-blue is-big.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ LA (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>)</h3>
<p>名前を示す語(またはセルブリ)を人や物を名前で示すスムティに変える描写型の冠詞。
<ppp>Descriptors which change name words (or selbri) into sumti which
identify people or things by name.</ppp>
LE に類似。
<ppp>Similar to LE.</ppp>
描写セルブリが後続する場合は KU によって終わらせることができる。
<ppp>May be terminated with KU if followed by a description selbri.</ppp>
<pre>la kikeros. du la tulis.
(キケロはタリーだ。)</pre>
<ppp>Cicero is Tully.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ LAU (<a href="./chapter17.html">第17章</a>)</h3>
<p>後続するアルファベットの文字と結びついて以下を示すマーカーとなる。
小文字から大文字への変化、フォントの変更、句読点等。
<ppp>Cmavo which combine with the following alphabetic letter to represent a
single marker: change from lower to upper case, change of font, punctuation,
etc.)</ppp>
<pre>tau sy. .ibu
(Si(硅素の化学記号))</pre>
<ppp>[single-shift] "s" "i"</ppp><ppp>Si(chemical symbol for silicon)</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ LAhE (<a href="./chapter6.html">第6章</a>)</h3>
<p>スムティに前置し、それを意味的に関係のある別のスムティに変える限定詞。
<ppp>Qualifiers which, when prefixed to a sumti, change it into another sumti
with related meaning.</ppp>
限定詞はまたセルマホ NAhE+BO からも作られる。
<ppp>Qualifiers can also consist of a cmavo from selma'o NAhE plus BO.</ppp>
LUhU も見よ。
<ppp>See LUhU.</ppp>
<pre>mi viska la'e zoi kuot. A Tale of Two Cities .kuot
(私は「二都物語」を見る。)</pre>
<ppp>I see that-represented-by the-text "A Tale of Two Cities".</ppp>
<ppp>I see the book "A Tale of Two Cities"</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ LE (<a href="./chapter6.html">第6章</a>)</h3>
<p>セルブリをそれの x1 に来る物を表すスムティに変える描写型の冠詞。
<ppp>Descriptors which make selbri into sumti which describe or specify things
that fit into the x1 place of the selbri.</ppp>
LA、KU を見よ。
<ppp>See LA, KU.</ppp>
<pre>le gerku klama le zdani
(その犬は家に行く。)</pre>
<ppp>The dog goes-to the house.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ LEhU (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>LOhU で始まる引用の終わりを示す。
<ppp>Indicates the end of a quotation begun with LOhU.</ppp>
省略できない終端子。
<ppp>Not an elidable terminator.</ppp>
<pre>lo'u mi du do du mi le'u cu na lojbo drani
(「mi du do du mi」はロジバンとして正しくない。)</pre>
<ppp>[quote]mi du do du mi[unquote] is-not Lojbanically correct.</ppp>
<ppp>"mi du do du mi" is not correct Lojban.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ LI (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>数字やその他の数式を数や数的表現を示すスムティに変える記述子。
<ppp>Descriptors which change numbers or other mathematical expressions into
sumti which specify numbers or numerical expressions.</ppp>
LOhO も見よ。
<ppp>See LOhO.</ppp>
<pre>li re su'u re na du li vo su'i vo
(2 - 2 &lt;&gt; 4 + 4)</pre>
<ppp>the-number  2 minus 2 not equals the-number 4 plus 4.</ppp>
<ppp>$2 - 2 &lt;&gt; 4 + 4$</ppp></p>
<!-- 60/121 -->
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ LIhU (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>
LU の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for LU.</ppp>
引用の終わりを示す。
<ppp>Indicates the end of a text quotation.</ppp>
<pre>mi cusku lu mi klama le zarci li'u
(私は「私は店に行く」と言う。)</pre>
<ppp>I express [quote] I go-to the market[end quote].</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ LOhO (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>
LI の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for LI. </ppp>
LI によって示される数式を終わりにする。
<ppp>Indicates the end of a mathematical expression used in a LI description.</ppp>
<pre>li vo lo'o li ci lo'o cu zmadu
(4 > 3)</pre>
<ppp>The-number 4 [end number], the number 3 [end number], is greater.</ppp>
<ppp>$4 &gt; 3$</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ LOhU (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>引用(スムティ)の始まりを示す。
この場合の引用はそれがロジバンにおける語から成るものであれば、
それが文の形を成しているかどうかに関わらず、文法的に正しいことになる。
<ppp>Indicates the beginning of a quotation (a sumti) which is grammatical
as long as the quoted material consists of Lojban words,
whether they form a text or not.</ppp>
LEhU で終わる。
<ppp>Terminated by LEhU.</ppp>
<pre>do cusku lo'u mi du do du ko'a le'u
(君は「mi du do du ko'a」と言う。)</pre>
<ppp>You express [quote] mi du do du ko'a [end quote].</ppp>
<ppp>You said, "mi du do du ko'a".</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ LU (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>
引用(スムティ)の始まりを示す。
この場合の引用は引用されている部分も文法的に正しいロジバンの文章でなければ、
文法的に正しくない。
<ppp>Indicates the beginning of a quotation (a sumti) whici is grammatical
only if the quoted material also forms a grammatical Lojban text.</ppp>
LIhU で終わる。
<ppp>Terminated by LIhU.</ppp>
<pre>mi cusku lu mi klama le zarci li'u
(私は「私は店に行く」と言う。)</pre>
<ppp>I express [quote] I go-to the market [end quote].</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ LUhU (<a href="./chapter6.html">第6章</a>)</h3>
<p>
LAhE や NAhE+BO の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for LAhE and NAhE+BO.</ppp>
限定スムティの終わりを示す。
<ppp>Indicates the end of a qualified sumti.</ppp>
<pre>mi viska la'e lu barda gerku li'u lu'u
(私は「大きい犬」(語ではなくこの題名の本または映画など)を見る。)</pre>
<ppp>I see the-referent-of [quote] big dog [end quote][end ref]</ppp>
<ppp>I saw "Big Dog" [not the words, but a book or movie].</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ MAI (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>, <a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>数字や文字の並びに後置し&free_modifier;を作る。
それは文章のインデックス番号となる。
<ppp>When suffixed to a number or string of letter words, produces a free modifier
which serves as an index number within a text.</ppp>
<pre>pamai mi pu klama le zarci
(1. 私は店に行った。)</pre>
<ppp>1-thly, I [past] go to-the market.</ppp>
<ppp>First, I went to the market.</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ MAhO (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>文字や他の被演算子から数学演算子を作る。
<ppp>Produces a mathematical operator from a letter or other operand.</ppp>
TEhU、VUhU も見よ。
<ppp>See TEhU, VUhU.</ppp>
<pre>ma'o fy. boi xy.
(f(x))</pre>
<ppp>[operator] f x</ppp>
<ppp>f(x)</ppp></p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ ME (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>, <a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>スムティからタンルの構成単位を作る。
それはスムティによって意味されるものに当てはまる。
<ppp>Produces a tanru unit from a sumti, which is applicable to the things
referenced by the sumti.</ppp>
MEhU も見よ。
<ppp>See MEhU.</ppp>
<pre>ta me la ford. karce
(あれはフォード車だ。)</pre>
<ppp>That is-a-Ford-type car</ppp>
<ppp>That's a Ford car.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: ここでは言及されていないが、
me はスムティからセルブリを作るのにも使われる。
というよりも、スムティをセルブリにすることで
タンルの要素にすることができるということだろう</chu><br/>
<chu># 訳注: do me la djan. は do du la djan. と同じ</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ MEhU (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>)</h3>
<p>ME の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>The elidable terminator for ME.</ppp>
タンルの構成単位へと変換されたスムティの末尾を示す。
<ppp>Indicates the end of a sumti converted to a tanru unit.</ppp>
<pre>ta me mi me'u zdani
(あれは私的な家だ。)</pre>
<ppp>That's a me type of house.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ MOI (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>)</h3>
<p>数やその他の量を示す語の後について、数に関するさまざまなセルブリを作る。
<ppp>Suffixes added to numbers or other quantifiers to make various
numerically-based selbri.</ppp>
<pre>la djan. joi la frank. cu bruna remei
(ジョンとフランクは2人兄弟だ。)</pre>
<ppp>John in-a-mass-with Frank are-a-brother-type-of twosome.</ppp>
<ppp>John and Frank are two brothers.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: mei は基数(2人、2本、2個、2匹等々)を示す</chu><br/>
<chu># 訳注: 上の例文は直訳すれば「ジョンとフランクは(兄弟であるような2人)だ」
となる</chu>
</p>
<!-- 70/121 -->
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ MOhE (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>スムティから数学被演算子をつくる。これは単位つきの量として使われる。
<ppp>Produces a mathematical operand from a sumti;
used to make dimensioned units.</ppp>
TEhU で終わる。
<ppp>Terminated by TEhU.</ppp>
<pre>li mo'e re ratcu su'i mo'e re ractu du li mo'e vo danlu
(2 鼠 + 2 兎 = 2 動物)</pre>
<ppp>the-number two rats plus two rabbits equals the-number four animals</ppp>
<ppp>2 rats + 2 rabbits = 4 animals.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: 「dimensioned unit」を「単位つきの量」と訳したが確信がない</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ MOhI (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>空間における動きを表す間制フラグ。動きの方向は後続する FAhA
シマヴォによって示す。
<ppp>A tense flag indicating movement in space, in a direction specified by
a following FAhA cmavo.</ppp>
<pre>le verba mo'i ri'u cadzu le bisli
(その子は氷の上を私の右の方へ歩く。)</pre>
<ppp>The child [movement][right] walks-on the ice.</ppp>
<ppp>The child walks toward my right on the ice.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ NA (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>, <a href="./chapter15.html">第15章</a>)</h3>
<p>矛盾否定。ブリディ全体を偽(または真)とする。
<ppp>Contradictory negators, asserting that a whole bridi is false (or true)</ppp>
<pre>mi na klama le zarci
(私は店に行かない。)</pre>
<ppp>it is not true that I go to the market.</ppp>
また、合成シマヴォとして論理的接続にも使われる。
<ppp>Also used to construct logical connective compound cmavo.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ NAI (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>, <a href="./chapter15.html">第15章</a>)</h3>
<p>先行する語を否定する。文法上、指定された特定のセルマホにのみつく。
<ppp>Negates the previous word, but can only be used with certain selma'o as
specified by the grammar.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ NAhE (<a href="./chapter15.html">第15章</a>)</h3>
<p>段階否定。セルブリやスムティを修飾し、それが示す状態から段階的な値へと変える。
例えばその状態の反対、等。
<ppp>Scalar negators, modifying a selbri or a sumti to a value other than
the one stated, the opposite of the one stated, etc.</ppp>
後続する BO とともにスムティ限定詞としても使う、LAhE も見よ。
<ppp>Also used with following BO to construct a sumti qualifier; see LAhE.</ppp>
<pre>ta na'e blanu zdani
(あれは青くない家だ。)</pre>
<ppp>That is-a-non-blue house.</ppp>
<ppp>That is a house which is other than blue.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ NAhU (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>
セルブリから数学演算子を作る。
<ppp>Creates a mathematical operator from a selbri.</ppp>
VUhU も見よ。
<ppp>See VUhU.</ppp>
<pre>li na'u tanjo te'u vei pai fe'i re[ve'o] du li ci'i
(tan(pi/2) = 無限大)</pre>
<ppp>the-number the-operator tangent(pi/2) = the-number infinity</ppp>
<ppp>tan(pi/2) = infinity</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ NIhE (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>
セルブリから数学被演算子を作る。たいていは ni により抽象化されたセルブリから。
<ppp>Creates a mathematical operand from a selbri, usually a "ni"
abstraction.</ppp>
TEhU で終わる。
<ppp>Terminated by TEhU.</ppp>
<pre>li ni'e ni clani [te'u] pi'i ni'e ni ganra [te'u]
pi'i ni'e ni condi te'u du li ni'e ni canlu
(長さ x 幅 x 深さ = 体積)</pre>
<ppp>the-number quantity-of length times quantity-of width times
quantity-of depth equals the-number quantity-of volume.</ppp>
<ppp>Length x Width x Depth = Volume</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ NIhO (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>新しい段落を示す。また、その段落が前の内容や新しい内容を含むかどうかを示す。
<ppp>Marks the beginning of new paragraph, and indicates whether it contains old
or new subject matter.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ NOI (<a href="./chapter8.html">第8章</a>)</h3>
<p>関係節を開始する。
<ppp>Relative clause introducers.</ppp>
後続するブリディは先行するスムティを修飾する。
<ppp>The following bridi modifies the preceding sumti.</ppp>
KUhO で終わる。
<ppp>Terminated by KUhO.</ppp>
GOI も見よ。
<ppp>See GOI.</ppp>
<pre>le zdani poi blanu cu cmalu
(その青い家は小さい。)</pre>
<ppp>The house which is blue is small</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ NU (<a href="./chapter11.html">第11章</a>)</h3>
<p>ブリディに前置して抽象セルブリを作る抽象詞。
<ppp>Abstractors which, when prefixed to a bridi, create abstraction selbri.</ppp>
KEI で終わる。
<ppp>Terminated by KEI.</ppp>
<pre>la djan. cu djica le nu sonci [kei]
(ジョンは兵士になることを望む。)</pre>
<ppp>John desires the event-of being-a-soldier.</ppp>
</p>

<!-- 80/121 -->
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ NUhA (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>
数学演算子からセルブリを作る。
<ppp>Create a selbri from a mathematical operator.</ppp>
VUhU も見よ。
<ppp>See VUhU.</ppp>
<pre>li ni'umu cu nu'a va'a li ma'umu
(数 -5 は 数 +5 の符号を反転したもの。)</pre>
<ppp>the-number -5 is the negation-of the-number +5</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ NUhI (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>, <a href="./chapter16.html">第16章</a>)</h3>
<p>
名辞組の始まりを示す。
名辞組はセルブリの2つかそれ以上の場所にスムティを同時に入れるために使われる。
<ppp>Marks the beginning of a termset, which is used to make simultaneous
claims involving two or more different places of a selbri</ppp>
<pre>mi klama nu'i le zarci le briju nu'u .e le zdani
le ckule [nu'u]
(私は店に事務所から行き、そして家に学校から行く。)</pre>
<ppp>I go [start] to-the market from-the office [joint] and to-the house
from-the school.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ NUhU (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<p>省略可能な NUhI の終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for NUhI.</ppp>
名辞組の終わりを示す。
またそれらの間に置かれて(論理的または非論理的接続詞による)名辞組の接続を示す。
<ppp>Marks the end of a termset, and is also used in the middle of one to mark
the termset joint (a logical or non-logical connective).</ppp>
<pre>mi klama nu'i le zarci le briju nu'u .e le zdani
le ckule [nu'u]
(私は店に事務所から行き、そして家に学校から行く。)</pre>
<ppp>I go [start] to-the market from-the office [joint] and to-the house
from-the schools)</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ PA (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>数字とそれに関連した&quantifier;(いくらかの、全ての、多くの等)。
<ppp>Digits and related quantifiers (some, all, many, etc.).</ppp>
<pre>mi speni re ninmu
(私は2人の女の人と結婚している。)</pre>
<ppp>I am-married-to two women.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ PEhE (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<p>論理的または非論理的接続詞の前について、2つの名辞組をつなぐ。
<ppp>Precedes a logical or non-logical connective that joins two termsets.</ppp>
名辞組はそれぞれの名辞を関係づけ、論理的に接続し、&quantifier;の掛かる範囲をまとめ、
または特別な間制の構造を作るために使われる(CEhe を見よ)。
<ppp>Termsets (see CEhE) are used to associate several terms for logical connectives,
for equal quantifier scope, or for special constructs in tenses.</ppp><br/>
<ppp>Joins multiple terms into a termset.</ppp>
<pre>mi ce'o do pe'e je la djan. ce'e la djeimys. cu pendo
(私は君の友達で、ジョンはジェームズの友達だ。)</pre>
<ppp>I [,] you [joint] and John [,] James are-friends-of.</ppp>
<ppp>I am a friend of you, and John is a friend of James.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ PEhO (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>任意で置くことができ、前置数学演算子を示す。前置演算子は被演算子の前に置かれる。
<ppp>An optional signal of forethought mathematical operators,
which precede their operands.</ppp>
KUhE で終わる。
<ppp>Terminated by KUhE.</ppp>
<pre>li vo du li pe'o su'i reboi re
(数 4 は数 2 と 2 の合計と等しい。)</pre>
<ppp>The-number four equals the-number [forethought] sum-of two two</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ PU (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>単純な時間の向き(未来、過去、それ以外)を示す。
<ppp>Specifies simple time directions (future, past, or neither)</ppp>
<pre>mi pu klama le zarci
(私は店に行った。)</pre>
<ppp>I [past] go-to the market.</ppp>
<ppp>I went to the market.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ RAhO (<a href="./chapter7.html">第7章</a>)</h3>
<p>代ブリディを更新するフラグ。代ブリディに暗黙につけられたスミティの意味を
前の文脈ではなく、新しい文脈に合うように変える。
<ppp>The pro-bridi update flag: changes the meaning of sumti implicitly
attached to a pro-bridi (see GOhA) to fit the current context rather than
the original context.</ppp>
<pre>A: mi ba lumci le mi karce B: mi go'i
(A: 私は私の車を洗う B: 私もそうする(A の車を洗う))</pre>
<ppp>A: I [future] wash my car. B: I do-the-same (i.e. wash A's car).</ppp>
<pre>A: mi ba lumci le mi karce B: mi go'i ra'o
(A: 私は私の車を洗う B: 私もそうする(B の車を洗う))</pre>
<ppp>A: I [future] wash my car. B: I do-the-corresponding-thing(i.e. wash B's car)</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ ROI (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>数に後置して拡張間制を表す(例: 1回、2回、何回も)。
<ppp>A particle which, when suffixed to a number, makes an extensional tense
(e.g. once, twice, many times).</ppp>
<pre>mi reroi klama le zarci
(私は2回その店に行く。)</pre>
<ppp>I twice go-to the market</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ SA (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>先行する句または文を取り消す。
<ppp>A particle which erases the previous phrase or sentence.</ppp>
<pre>mi klama sa do klama le zarci
(私は行く、いや違う、君が店に行く。)</pre>
<ppp>I go, er, you go-to the market.</ppp>
</p>

<!-- 90/121 -->
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ SE (<a href="./chapter5.html">第5章</a>)</h3>
<p>
セルブリの x1 とその他の場所を入れ換える。
<ppp>Particles which convert a selbri, rearranging the order of places by
exchanging the x1 place with a specified numbered place.</ppp>
<pre>le zarci se klama mi
(その店は私によって行かれた。)</pre>
<ppp>The market is-gone-to by me</ppp>
複合的な接続詞や法制シマヴォにも使われる。
<ppp>Also used in constructing connective and modal compound cmavo.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ SEI (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>ブリディに対するメタ的なコメントの開始する。
<ppp>Marks the beginning of metalinguistic insertions which comment on
the main bridi.</ppp>
SEhU で終わる。
<ppp>Terminated by SEhU.</ppp>
<pre>la frank. prami sei gleki [se'u] la djein.
(フランク(彼は幸せだ)はジェーンを愛している。)</pre>
<ppp>Frank loves (he is happy) Jane.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: どうしてここで se'u が省略できるのか</chu><br/>
<chu># 訳注: la djein. が gleki の x2 とならないのは何故か</chu><br/>
<chu># 訳注: gleki の x2 には抽象スムティしか来ないから、か</chu><br/>
<chu># 訳注: PEG を読めばわかるかもしれない。</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ SEhU (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>
SEI や SOI の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for SEI and SOI.</ppp>
メタ的な挿入を終わらせる。
<ppp>Ends metalinguistic insertions.</ppp>
<pre>la frank. prami sei gleki se'u la djein.
(フランク(彼は幸せだ)はジェーンを愛している。)</pre>
<ppp>Frank loves (he is happy) Jane.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ SI (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>先行する語ひとつを取り消す。
<ppp>A particle which erases the previous single word.</ppp>
<pre>mi si do klama le zarci
(私、いや、君が店に行く。)</pre>
<ppp>I, er, you go to-the market.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ SOI (<a href="./chapter7.html">第7章</a>)</h3>
<p>2つのスムティの相互関係を示す(英語の「vice versa」に近い)。
<ppp>Marks reciprocity between two sumti (like "vice versa" in English).</ppp>
<pre>mi prami do soi mi
(私はあなたを愛していて、そしてあなたも私を愛している。)</pre>
<ppp>I love you [reciprocally] me.</ppp>
<ppp>I love you and vice versa.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: soi の二番目の引数は直前のスムティが入る</chu>
<br/><chu># 訳注: つまり上記は mi prami do soi mi do となり、</chu>
<br/><chu># 訳注: mi prami do であり、その mi と do を入れ換えても真である、となる</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ SU (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>先行する談話を終わらせ、その全てを取り消す。
<ppp>A particle which closes and erases the entire previous discourse.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ TAhE (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>時間または空間の範囲内での頻度(規則的に、習慣的に、等)を表す間制限定詞。
<ppp>A tense modifier specifying frequencies within an interval of time or
space (regularly, habitually, etc.).</ppp>
<pre>le verba ta'e klama le ckule
(その子供は習慣的に学校に行く。)</pre>
<ppp>The child habitually goes to-the school.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ TEI (<a href="./chapter17.html">第17章</a>)</h3>
<p>
複合的に構成された文字を表す語列を始める。
その語列は文法的にはひとつの文字として扱われる。
<ppp>Signals the beginning of a compound letter word, which acts
grammatically like a single letter.</ppp>
語列は省略できないセルマホ FOI で終わる。
<ppp>Compound letter words end with the non-elidable selma'o FOI.</ppp>
<pre>tei .ebu .akut. bu foi
(アキュートアクセントつきの e)</pre>
<ppp>("e" "acute")</ppp>
<ppp>the letter "e" with an acute accent</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ TEhU (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>JOhI、MAhO、MOhE、NAhU、NIhE の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for JOhI, MAhO, MOhE, NAhU, or NIhE.</ppp>
数式への変換の終わりを示す。
<ppp>Marks the end of a mathematical conversion construct.</ppp>
<pre>li joi' paboi reboi te'u su'i jo'i ciboi voboi
du li jo'i voboi xaboi
((1, 2) + (3, 4) = (4, 6))</pre>
<ppp>the-number array (one, two) plus array (three, four) equals the number
array (four, six)</ppp>
<ppp>(1, 2) + (3, 4) = (4, 6)</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ TO (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>談話系における左かっこ。主題からずれた話を挿入する。
<ppp>Left discursive parenthesis: allows inserting a digression.</ppp>
TOI で終わる。
<ppp>Terminated by TOI.</ppp>
<pre>doi lisas. mi djica le nu to doi frank. ko sisti
toi do viska le mlatu
(リサ、私はあなたに(フランク! やめなさい)猫を見せたい。)</pre>
<ppp>O Lisa, I desire the event-of (O Frank, [imperative] stop!) you see the cat.</ppp>
<ppp>Lisa, I want you to (Frank! Stop!) see the cat.</ppp>
</p>

<!-- 100/121 -->
</item>

<item>
<h3>セルマホ TOI (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>TO の省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for TO.</ppp>
談話系における右かっこ。
<ppp>The right discursive parenthesis.</ppp>
<pre>doi lisas. mi djica le nu to doi frank. ko sisti
toi do viska le mlatu
(リサ、私はあなたに(フランク! やめなさい)猫を見せたい。)</pre>
<ppp>O Lisa, I desire the event-of (O Frank, [imperative] stop!) you see the cat.</ppp>
<ppp>Lisa, I want you to (Frank! Stop!) see the cat.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ TUhE (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>複数の文や段落を論理的にまとめる。
<ppp>Groups multiple sentences or paragraphs into a logical unit.</ppp>
TUhU で終わる。
<ppp>Terminated by TUhU.</ppp>
<pre>xagmau zo'u tu'e ganai cidja gi cnino .i ganai
vanju gi tolci'o [tu'u]
(最良なのは、食事は新しいもので、ワインは古いものだ。)</pre>
<ppp>is-best: [start] if food, then new. if wine, then old [is bes].</ppp>
<ppp>As for what is best: if food, then new [is best]; if wine, then old [is best]</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: 最良なものである: (それは食事ではない または 新しい) かつ
(それはワインではない または 古い)</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ TUhU (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>TUhE の論理的終端子。
<ppp>Logical terminator for TUhE.</ppp>
複数の文のグループの終わりを示す。
<ppp>Marks the end of a multiple sentence group.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ UI (<a href="./chapter13.html">第13章</a>)</h3>
<p>話者の感情的な状態、知識の出所、談話における局面を示す。
<ppp>Particles which indicate the speaker's emotional state or source of
knowledge, or the present stage of discourse.</ppp>
<pre>.ui la djan. klama
(やった、ジョンが来る。)</pre>
<ppp>[Happiness!] John is-coming.</ppp>
<ppp>Hurrah! John is coming!</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ VA (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>空間的な距離を示す間制(近い、遠い、どちらでもない)。
<ppp>A tense indicating distance in space (near, far, or neither).</ppp>
<pre>le nanmu va batci le gerku
(そこで男が犬をかむ。)</pre>
<ppp>The man [medium distance] bites the dog.</ppp>
<ppp>Over there the man is biting the dog</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: va のなかに ca が含まれているのかもしれない。調べること</chu><br/>
<chu># 訳注: そういうことではなく、単に文脈から英語訳が is biting
になっているだけか</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ VAU (<a href="./chapter14.html">第14章</a>)</h3>
<p>単純なブリディまたは GIhA による論理的接続におけるブリディ末端の
省略可能な終端子。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for a simple bridi, or for each bridi-tail of a GIhA
logical connection.</ppp>
<pre>mi dunda le cukta [vau] gi'e lebna lo rupnu vau do [vau]
(私はあなたに本をあげて、お金を取る。)</pre>
<ppp>I (givce the book) and (take some currency-units) to/from you.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ VEI (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>数学の左かっこ。数学演算をまとめる。
<ppp>Left mathematical parenthesis: groups mathematical operations.</ppp>
VEhO で終わる。
<ppp>Terminated by VEhO.</ppp>
<pre>li vei ny. su'i pa ve'o pi'i vei ny. su'i pa
[ve'o] du li ny. [bo] te'a re su'i re bo pi'i ny.
su'i pa
((n + 1)(n + 1) = n ^ 2 + 2 n + 1)</pre>
<ppp>the-number ("n" plus one) times ("n" plus one) equals the-number
n-power-two plus two-times-"n" plus 1</ppp>
<ppp>$(n + 1)(n + 1) = n^2 + 2n + 1$</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ VEhA (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>
空間における距離(長、中、短)を示す間制詞。
<ppp>A tense indicating the size of an interval in space (long, medium, or short)</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ VEhO (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>VEI の省略可能な終端子。数学の右かっこ。
<ppp>Elidable terminator for VEI: right mathematical parenthesis.</ppp>
<pre>li vei ny. su'i pa ve'o pi'i vei ny. su'i pa
[ve'o] du li ny. [bo] te'a re su'i re bo pi'i ny.
su'i pa
((n + 1)(n + 1) = n ^ 2 + 2 n + 1)</pre>
<ppp>the-number ("n" plus one) times ("n" plus one) equals the-number
n-power-two plus two-times-"n" plus 1</ppp>
<ppp>$(n + 1)(n + 1) = n^2 + 2n + 1$</ppp>
<pp></pp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ VIhA (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>空間における次元(線上、面上、空間上、時空上の間隔)を示す間制。
<ppp>A tense indicating dimensionality in space(line, plane, volume, or
space-time interval)</ppp>
<pre>le verba ve'a vi'a cadzu le bisli
(中くらいの範囲で、氷の上をその子は歩く。)</pre>
<ppp>The child [medium space interval][2-dimensional] walks-on the ice.</ppp>
<ppp>In a medium-sized area, the child walks on the ice.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<!-- 110/121 -->
<h3>セルマホ VUhO (<a href="./chapter8.html">第8章</a>)</h3>
<p>関係節や関係句が、スムティの最も左側の部分ではなく、
(複合的であるかもしれない)スムティ全体にかかるようにする。
<ppp>A mechanism for attaching relative clauses or phrases to a whole
(possibly connected) sumti, rather than simply to the leftmost portion of
the sumti.</ppp>
<pre>la frank. ce la djordi. vu'o noi gidva cu zvati le kumfa
(フランクとジョージは、彼らはガイドであるのだが、部屋にいる。)</pre>
<ppp>Frank [in-set-with] George, which are-guides, are-in the room.</ppp>
<ppp>Frank and George, who are guides, are in the room.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ XI (<a href="./chapter18.html">第18章</a>)</h3>
<p>下付き文字のしるし。後続する数字やレルフ列は何が前に来ようとも下付きとなる。
<ppp>The subscript marker: the following number or lerfu string is a
subscript for whatever precedes it.</ppp>
<pre>xy. xi re
(x<sub>2</sub>)</pre>
<pp>x sub 2</pp>
<pp>x<sub>2</sub></pp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ Y (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>ためらいの音。意味はないが話を続けたり会話を続けるために使われる。
<ppp>Hesitation noise: content-free, but holds the floor or continues the
conversation.</ppp>
沈黙とは、沈黙がそれ以上言うことがないというように解釈される点で異なる。
<ppp>It is different from silence in that silence may be
interpreted as having nothing more to say.</ppp>
<pre>doi .y. .y. djan
(やあ、ええと、ええと、ジョン!)
</pre>
<ppp>O, uh, uh, John!</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ ZAhO (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>出来事が事象線上のどこにあるか(例: 始まり、終わり、持続)を示す間制修飾詞。
<ppp>A tense modifier specifying the contour of an event
(e.g. beginning, ending, continuing).</ppp>
<pre>mi pu'o damba
(ちょうど今から戦うところだ。)</pre>
<ppp>[inchoative] fight.</ppp>
<ppp>I'm on the verge of fighting.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: pu'o は起動相であり何かをする直前を意味する</chu>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<!-- 114/121 -->

<h3>セルマホ ZEI (<a href="./chapter4.html">第4章</a>)</h3>
<p>形態学的な接着語。両側にある語をルジヴォと同じ意味でつなげる。
<ppp>A morphological glue word, which joins the two words it stands
between into the equivalent of a lujvo.</ppp>
<pre>ta xy. zei kantu kacma
(あれはX線カメラだ。)</pre>
<ppp>That is-an-(X - ray) camera.</ppp>
<ppp>That is an X-ray camera.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ ZEhA (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>時の範囲(長、中、短)という間制を示す。
<ppp>A tense indicating the size of an interval in time (long, medium, or short).
</ppp>
<pre>mi puze'a citka
(私は短い時間食事をした。)</pre>
<ppp>I [past] [short interval] eat.</ppp>
<ppp>I ate for a little while.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ ZI (<a href="./chapter10.html">第10章</a>)</h3>
<p>時の隔たり(遠い、中くらいの、近い過去または未来)という間制を示す。
<ppp>A tense indicating distance in time (a long, medium or short time
ago or in the future).</ppp>
<pre>mi puzi citka
(ついさっき食事をしたところだ。)</pre>
<ppp>I [past] [short distance] eat.</ppp>
<ppp>I ate a little while ago.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ ZIhE (<a href="./chapter8.html">第8章</a>)</h3>
<p>同じスムティに掛かる関係句や関係節をまとめる。
<ppp>Joins multiple relative phrases or clauses which apply to the same sumti.</ppp>
英訳の際には「and」と訳されることが多いが、論理的接続とは見なされない。
<ppp>Although it is generally translated with "and", it is not considered
a logical connective.</ppp>
<pre>mi ponse pa gerku ku poi blabi zi'e noi mi prami ke'a
(私は白い犬を飼っていて、私はそれを愛している。)</pre>
<ppp>I own one dog such-that it-is-white and such-that-incidentally I love it.</ppp>
<ppp>I own a dog that is white and which, incidentally, I love.</ppp>
<ppp>I own a white dog, which I love.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ ZO (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>後続するロジバンの一語をクォートする。
<ppp>Single-word quotation: quotes the following single Lojban word.</ppp>
<pre>zo si cu lojbo valsi
(語「si」はロジバンの語である。)</pre>
<ppp>The-word "si" is-a-Lojbanic word.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ ZOI (<a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>ロジバン以外を取るクォーター:
区切り文字(ロジバンの語なら何でも良い)を前後に使ってあらゆる文字列をクォートする。
<ppp>Non-Lojban quotation: quotes any text using a delimiting word
(which can be any single Lojban word) placed before and after the text.</ppp>
区切り文字は文字列中に出てきてはならない、また文字列との間に停止が必要。
<ppp>The delimiting word must not appear in the text, and must be
separated from the text by pauses.</ppp>
<pre>zoi kuot. Socrates is mortal .kuot. cu glico jufra
(「Socrates is mortal」は英語の文章だ。)</pre>
<ppp>The-text "Socrates is mortal" is-an-English sentence.</ppp>
</p>
</item>

<item>

<h3>セルマホ ZOhU (<a href="./chapter16.html">第16章</a>, <a href="./chapter19.html">第19章</a>)</h3>
<p>論理的冠頭部をそれが適用されるブリディや文のまとまりから分ける。
<ppp>Separates a logical prenex from a bridi or group of sentences to
which it applies.</ppp>
または、主題/評言文において、主題を主題に対する評言から分ける。
<ppp>Also separates a topic from a comment in topic/comment sentences.</ppp>
<pre>su'o da poi remna ro de poi finpe zo'u da prami de
(全ての魚を好む人がいる。)</pre>
<ppp>For-at-least-one X which is-a-man, for-all Ys which are-fish: X loves Y</ppp>
<ppp>There is a man who loves all fish.</ppp>
<chu># 訳注: 底本では su'o da poi remna ro &lt;da&gt; poi finpe zo'u da prami de
だが da でなくて de だろう。</chu>
</p>
</item>

<!-- 121/121 -->
<after>
<chu>#29 note: optional と elidable の訳し分けは必要か</chu><br/>
<chu># note: 上記は同じ意味として良さそう</chu><br/>
<chu>#30 note: ロジバンでは意志と未来とは明確に分けられているのだろうか</chu><br/>
<chu>#31 note: デフォルトでは分かれてなくて、それを分けるための構文が別にあるのか</chu>
<br/>
<chu>#32 note: あるいは、英語の「will」とは違い、ba には意志の意味はないのか</chu>
<chu>#33 note: その場合でも聞き手の解釈によって ba に意志を読み込んでも良いのか、
またはそれは許されないのか</chu><br/>
<chu>#34 note: しかし、単純な未来とは何か。
意志も予測も含まれない単純な未来という概念は成立するだろうか</chu><br/>
<chu>#35 note: particle をどう訳すか。文法要素とか、か</chu><br/>
<chu>#36 note: metalinguistic をどう訳すか</chu><br/>
<chu>#37 note: tense modifier を間制修飾詞と訳した</chu><br/>
<chu>#38 note: tense indicater を間制詞と訳した</chu><br/>
<chu>#39 note: (e.g. ...) と (... etc.) を訳し分ける必要があるか。両方とも (... 等)で
良いかもしれない</chu><br/>
<chu>#40 note: quote を「引用する」と訳すのは適切か。
「クォートする」と訳しておいた場所もあるが再考の必要あり</chu><br/>
<chu>#41 note: quotation を「quote するもの」ということで「クォーター」と訳した箇所が
あるが、もちろん、あまり良い訳ではない。要再考</chu><br/>
<chu>#42 note: quantifier をどう訳すか。「&quantifier;」としておくか</chu><br/>
<chu>#43 note: 「特別な間制の構造」は "special constructs in tenses"
の訳だがよくわからない</chu><br/>
<chu>#44 note: 名辞組の要素として間制も取れるということか。例文が必要</chu>
</after>
</body_>

</body>
</chapter>
